A Guide to the Papers of Carter Glass 1858-1946, and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Correspondence (Box 43)
  A. Letter of Harvey A. Wheeler, 8 August 1913, containing valuable material relative to Carter Glass bill and attitude of banks to its requirements; Letter, Carter Glass to O. M. W. Sprague; Letter, Fiske to Carter Glass relative to Colonel House; Letter of Carter Glass to Senator Simmons regarding liberty bonds; Letter, Laughlin to Carter Glass regarding reserves of Reserve Banks; Letter of J. H. Tregoe, secretary- treasurer of the National Association of Credit Men, mentions an analysis of the Federal Reserve Act to be published in the Association magazine; Portion of the minutes of the Democratic house caucus relates to changes in the Act; Letter, Morawitz to Carter Glass; Letter, O. M. W. Sprague to Carter Glass, 10 June 1913; Letter from Reynolds regarding balances in other banks as reserves; Letter from Speyer and Company; Clipping from St. Louis Republic regarding Carter Glass' answer to Senator Reed; Editorial, Ocala, Florida, 23 December 1913; Report on action of the Conference Committee on the Federal Reserve bill; Letter, William A. Scott to Carter Glass regarding draft of bill for a central bank; Letter of George P. McLellan to Carter Glass regarding speech at Bremerton; Letter, W. A. Scott to Carter Glass on weaknesses in the banking system; Letter, Benjamin Strong to Carter Glass; Speech by Carter Glass "a Republican invention exposed," 7 September 1916, with annotations by Carter Glass; Letter, W. W. Hoxton to Carter Glass, 17 January 19127; Letter, H. Parker Willis to Carter Glass, 14 December 1918, regarding treasury.
- Correspondence on banking and currency (Box 44)
  A. Telegram from George M. Reynolds on September 21, 1914, opposing the attempt to incorporate a provision against interlocking bank directorates in the Clayton bill, Carter Glass responds that he will oppose the move; Booklet prepared on April 2, 1914, containing the plan decided upon by the organizational committee for the division of the country into twelve districts and the location of the Federal Reserve banks; Letter from a Texas banker on August 27, 1914, complaining of the provision requiring a bank to hold a certain percentage of its capital stock and surplus in order to become a member of the Federal Reserve System; Letter from William L. Boss on September 20, 1914, expressing concern over the failure of the Federal Reserve Board to act favorably upon his proposals for organization; Telegrams to Representative R. L. Henry during September, 1914, concerning emergency currency issues for agricultural purposes; Telegram of August 19, 1914, requesting that state banks be admitted to membership in the National Currency Association. Carter Glass notes that such a proposal has already been made; Letters from Charles A. Conant during August, 1914, concerning reserves, note issue, and gold certificates, expressing the desire to protect the gold reserve. Carter Glass answers that questions of tax rates on notes are difficult to handle. Charles A. Conant does not want the use of gold certificates encouraged in lieu of notes by a high tax rate on note issue; Carter Glass answers a question raised by a banker, concerning the reasoning behind a limit on the loans which could be made by a bank, according to its capital and surplus; Copy of a speech by Senator Cummings, September 29, 1914, expressing dissatisfaction with the manner in which the popular interests have been ignored by the members of the Federal Reserve Board. Carter Glass finds no specific criticism to which he could reply; Letter from W. B. Doak, September 9, 1921, complaining that the American farmer is still at a competitive disadvantage with foreign interests, despite the Federal Reserve Act; Letter from Carter Glass, September 25, 1914, to Fredrick E. Farnsworth, tentatively accepting a speaking engagement and stating that he feels that great care must be exercised to prevent the alteration of the Federal Reserve Act in an unfavorable manner; Note from Charles S. Hamlin of the Federal Reserve Board, August 29, 1914, enclosing several proposed amendments to the Federal Reserve Act, and including a paper questioning the wisdom of opening the new banks immediately; Letter from William W. Flannagan, August 15, 1914, expressing the opinion that it would be a mistake to permit Federal Reserve notes to count as a part of the legal Reserve; Letter Carter Glass to Congressman Scott Ferris, July 8, 1914, regarding the holding of postal deposits by non-member state banks and relating to the Mondell bill; Amendment to the section of the Federal Reserve Act, setting forth the requirements for trust operations by national banks, suggested on August 31, 1914, by George C. Gregory; Reply, May 19, 1914, by Carter Glass to a letter from M. Brayton Graff, refusing a request to consider a bill not officially introduced in the House, unless Henry would agree to allow the Banking and Currency Committee to consider three bills favorably and report them to the House floor; Telegram, September 21, 1914, from E. D. Hulbert requesting assurance that Carter Glass opposes the prohibition against interlocking bank directorates. Carter Glass responds affirmatively; Letter to A. Barton Hepburn, September 14, 1914, explaining the attitudes of several groups toward the inclusion of Federal Reserve notes among reserves and promising that his committee would defeat any such proposal; Carter Glass to E. D. Hulbert, September 9, 1914, expressing full agreement with E. D. Hulbert on the question of reserves; Telegram, Carter Glass to A. Barton Hepburn, asking the position of the bankers on the question of counting Federal Reserve notes as reserve, answer by A. Barton Hepburn that most bankers in New York so desire. Subsequent letter from Carter Glass stating his view of the problem in terms of "dilution of bank reserves and resultant inflation." Glass does not support the thinking of Paul M. Warburg on the subject, although he thus comes into conflict with the Federal Reserve Board; Telegram, August 13, 1914, from A. Barton Hepburn, giving an analysis of the problem allowing bank notes to be used as reserves by national banks, a practice which Hepburn opposes; Answering telegram from Carter Glass expressing agreement with A. Barton Hepburn; Telegram from E. D. Hulbert, August 5, 1914, requesting that a proposed amendment to section 19 of the Federal Reserve Act be given consideration as soon as possible; In response to a question concerning the possibility of farmers borrowing money at a lower rate of interest, Carter Glass states that legislation along this line is pending, but that he doubts the value of the proposals; Copy of a plan for the establishment of a national Land Mortgage Bank, sent to Carter Glass on May 7, 1914, by John V. Hogan; Letter, April 16, 1914, Carter Glass stating that he has been experiencing difficulty keeping up with his correspondence, because of the necessity for explaining the provisions of the Federal Reserve Act to the business men of the country; Letter, March 24, 1914, from E. D. Hulbert, asking about the status of an amendment, upon the preparation of which he and Carter Glass had agreed; Letter from Richard W. Knott, editor of the Evening Post in Louisville, Kentucky, September 30, 1914, relating to the problem of changing the location of bank reserves, stating that the vaults of the individual bank are the proper place for reserves to be held, oppossing Paul M. Warburg's opinion that the Federal Reserve bank of the district should have control over the reserve fund, and mentioning Stanley Matthews, John Sherman, and Schiff; Answer from Carter Glass agreeing in part with Knott, but considers the proposed changes as less serious than does Knott; Several other letters from Richard W. Knott deal with this subject; In answer to a question as to how much capital stock a state bank must have before qualifying for membership in the Federal Reserve System, Carter Glass states that the requirements are the same as for national banks; Amendment suggested by Representative A. W. Lafferty, with the aim of making membership requirements somewhat less severe for state banks; Letter, Carter Glass to William G. McAdoo, secretary of the Treasury, October 6, 1914, discussing the plan by which Representative Henry would have the Federal Reserve System extend loans to cotton producers; Letter opposing the issue of emergency currency by state banks; Letter, Carter Glass to Richard W. Knott, September 25, 1914, concerning the advisability of amending the Federal Reserve Act to enable member banks to deposit any part of their reserve fund at the reserve banks. Carter Glass felt that, in view of the war in Europe, such action would be acceptable; Letter, August 22, 1914, from William G. McAdoo, suggesting that a higher percent of commercial paper be permitted to be held as security for circulating notes, with a corresponding lowering of the requirements for bonds or other securities. Easier financing of farm crops was expected to be the result; Letter, Carter Glass to G. W. Musser on July 9, 1914, praising H. H. Seldomridge, a member of the Banking and Currency Committee; Amendments suggested on May 14, 1914, by Herbert Myrick to the Federal Farm Finance Act. Carter Glass responds; Note from William G. McAdoo, April 24, 1914, accompanying a memorandum on the proposed Farm Loan Associations; Several other notes from W. G. McAdoo, written during April, 1914; Letter from William G. McAdoo, March 16,1914, enclosing two proposed amendments to the Federal Reserve Act, dealing with the discounting of acceptances growing out of foreign trade and the amount of reserves held by national banks and state banks; Letter from the American Bankers Association, September 28, 1914, concerning interlocking directorates, the continuance of which the bankers favored; Letter from Representative Edmund Platt on September 23, 1914, expressing regret at being unable to attend a meeting of the Banking and Currency Committee; Letter, July 9, 1914, to D. C. Pryor, regarding the disapproval of President Wilson for the Bulkley rural credits bill and answering inquiries concerning Congressmen Thompson and Weaver. Pryor's letter posed three questions; Statement, prepared by E. A. Paffrath on May 22, 1914, containing several points relating to loans to farmers; Copy of a letter from E. F. Rines to Senator Robert L. Owen on August 28, 1914, suggesting an amendment to the section of the Aldrich-Vreeland Act dealing with security for circulation notes; Letter from Channning Rudd, June 11, 1914, quoting O. M. W. Sprague as saying that legislation, relating to the unification of circulating currency, is pending, is answered negatively by Carter Glass; Letter of June 10, 1914, from A. F. Robson, asking that banks be permitted to continue holding postal savings funds; Letter from Channing Rudd on June 13, 1914, asking what the intent of the Federal Reserve Act was with respect to the retirement of national bank notes. Carter Glass answers that banks can increase their notes in circulation as long as they can find government 2's to secure the notes; Petition, June 16, 1914, favoring the proposed rural credit law transmitted to Carter Glass by Representative Stout; Correspondence, largely with George J. Seay and Oliver J. Sands, relating to the acceptance of Richmond, Virginia, as the cite for a Federal Reserve Bank; Letter from C. W. York, June 17, 1914, announcing a plan for a National Land Bank and Insurance Company; J. H. Tregoe of the National Association of Credit Men on September 18, 1914, requested the opinion of Carter Glass on certain amendments to the Federal Reserve Act; Other correspondence with Tregoe; Letter from Representative Oscar W. Underwood on September 23, 1914, in behalf of a bank which was said to have too little surplus, along with a copy of the letter cited by Underwood; Letter from S. W. Welch, to Oscar W. Underwood, concerning loans on cotton crops; Memorandum prepared on August 13, 1954, for the Secretary of the Treasury, by >M. C. Elliot, concerning what might be acceptable as security for circulating notes under the provisions of the Aldrich-Vreeland Act; Telegram from Representative Oscar W. Underwood, August 19, 1914, concerning membership for state banks and the more liberal use of commercial paper as backing for emergency currency; Carter Glass to Joseph P. Tumulty, May 14, 1914, discussing the attitudes of the President, Bulkley, and a three-member committee; Paper containing the recommendation of the National Association of Credit Men, concerning rediscounting; Telegrams, April 9, 1914, from John Skelton Williams as comptroller of the Currency; Telegram, July 29, 1914, from Paul M. Warburg; Letter to H. Parker Willis from Carter Glass, July 9, 1914, requesting further information on activities of the Monetary Commission; Letter, Carter Glass to H. Parker Willis, July 9, 1914, stating in confidence that William G. McAdoo is considering H. Parker Willis for the position of secretary to the Federal Reserve Board. H. Parker Willis is assured of a good job somewhere in the system, possibly at New York; Letter, June 20, 1914, to Carter Glass from H. Parker Willis asking that Carter Glass give certain information to H. Parker Willis, on the basis of which he can take action; Notes from John Skelton Williams, Comptroller of the Currency, in May and June, 1914; Statement by John Skelton Williams, May 29, 1914, stating that the office of the comptroller of the Currency has not discriminated against Baltimore, Maryland, in the matter of locating
- Correspondence and Photographss of Woodrow Wilson and William G. McAdoo 1913 (Box 45)
  A. Woodrow Wilson to Carter Glass, expressing appreciation for his work on the Federal Reserve Act.
  B. Letter from William G. McAdoo to Carter Glass, giving Glass credit for the pushing through of the Federal Reserve Act.
- Correspondence (Box 46A)
  A. Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding collaboration by H. Parker Willis; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding the shares of a Federal Reserve to be held by a bank that is no longer a member bank; Letter, Tom McAdams to Carter Glass regarding the address to the Reserve City Bankers Association; Letter, Tom McAdams to Carter Glass regarding earnings of Federal Reserve Banks; Letter from Tom McAdams to Carter Glass regarding interest on savings accounts; Tom McAdams to Carter Glass regarding the making of National Banks receivers in the case of bankruptcy of other banks; Carter Glass to Tom McAdams regarding earnings and dividends of Reserve Banks; Tom McAdams to Carter Glass regarding earnings and dividends of Reserve Banks, January, 1929; Tom McAdams to Carter Glass regarding state legislation antagonistic to National Banks; Tom McAdams to Carter Glass regarding the authorization of state banks and trust companies to act as depositories for Federal Reserve banks; Tom McAdams to Carter Glass regarding the weak position of National Banks; Tom McAdams to Carter Glass regarding the taxation of Banks; Tom McAdams to Carter Glass and vice versa on the McFadden Act; Carter Glass to Tom McAdams regarding the position of Federal Reserve agent; Carter Glass to Tom McAdams regarding attitude of President Warren G. Harding toward Federal Reserve System; Carter Glass to Tom McAdams regarding the appointment of chairman of the Board; Tom McAdams to Carter Glass regarding members of the Board of Governors, 1 January 1923; Letter from Preshaker to Senator Lenroot regarding appointments to the Board of Governors; Tom McAdams to Governor W. P. G. Harding regarding par collection, etc.; Letter from Tom McAdams to Carter Glass regarding the three basic complaints against reserve banks; Carter Glass to Tom McAdams, reference to Senator Reed's campaign and the injection of the Federal Reserve System into the election campaign; Tom McAdams to Carter Glass regarding plans to resist the tax on Federal Reserve System; Tom McAdams to Carter Glass regarding perpetual charters for National Banks; Tom McAdams to Carter Glass, 20 December 1921, regarding reappointment of Harding; McAdams to Carter Glass, 7 December 1920, regarding discount rate charged by Atlanta; Tom McAdams to Carter Glass, 9 August 1920, regarding regulation of interest rates charged by banks.
- Correspondence (Box 46B)
  A. Eugene Meyer to Carter Glass, 7 May 1932, regarding changes in Glass bill; Samuel Untermeyer to Carter Glass, 31 May 1932, regarding affiliates of banks; Letter from Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 18 March 1938, regarding funds for H. Parker Willis memorial; Letter from Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 25 January 1938, regarding the holding companies; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 4 February 1937, regarding administration policy on gold and the Federal Reserve; Memorandum by Edmund Platt on the conflict of laws regarding holding companies; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding new members on the Board of Governors, 29 January 1936; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding the article in the Herald Tribune, 26 December 1935; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 2 January 1936; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 3 February 1935, regarding open market; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding H. Parker Willis and others, 26 July 1934; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 16 April 1935, regarding gold standard, etc.; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass relative to Herald Tribune article, 16 April 1935, relative to gold standard; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass relative to Echols, 22 March 1935; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass relative to interest on time deposits, 3 January 1935; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 7 June 1934, relative to clipping on the Warren study of closed banks; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding industrial loans by Reserve banks, 4 May 1934; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding Platt letter in Herald Tribune, 30 April 1934, on creating credit; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding industrial loans, 30 March 1934; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding confiscation of gold, 18 January 1934; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding terms of board members; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding branch banking; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding branch banking, 3 January 1933; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 4 November 1932, regarding branch banking; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 13 July 1932, regarding branch banking; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 18 February 1933, regarding branch banking; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 24 January 1933, regarding branch banking; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding trust companies, February, 1933; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, Journal of Commerce, 23 January 1933; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 26 May 1932; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 9 April 1932; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 20 February 1932, regarding emergency banking act.
- Correspondence (Box 46C)
  A. Letter of Samuel Untermeyer to Carter Glass regarding bank affiliates under the Glass bill; Letter to Eugene Myer regarding changes in Carter Glass bill; Letter from Edmund Platt to Carter Glass regarding memorial for H. Parker Willis, 18 March 1938, also regarding holding companies; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 8 October 1938; Platt to Glass, 25 January 1938; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 4 February 1937; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 21 December 1936, regarding branch banking; Manuscript by Edmund Platt on holding companies and the Glass bill; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 17 April 1938, regarding branch banking; Platt to Glass, 29 January 1936, regarding new members of the board; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 2 January 1936, on several matters; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 3 July 1935, regarding the open market; Platt to Glass, 22 March 1935, approval of Echols; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 16 April 1935, regarding the Act of 1935; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 17 February 1935, on same subject; Platt to Glass, 8 January 1935, regarding interest on savings deposits; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 9 June 1934, regarding Warren's study of liquidity of banks; Platt to Glass, 19 March 1934, regarding credit; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 13 January 1934, on abandonment of gold; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 18 January 1934; Platt to Glass, 20 September 1930, regarding terms of members of the board; 14 March 1933, final form of Glass bill; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 3 January 1933, regarding branch banking; Platt to Glass, 4 November 1932, regarding branch banking; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 13 July 1932, regarding the University of Virginia and Institute of Public Affairs; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 18 February 1933, regarding branch banking and the Carter Glass bill; Platt to Glass, 14 May 1932, regarding series in Commercial and Financial Chronicle, 4 November 1921; Edmund Platt to Carter Glass, 9 April 1932, regarding branch banking.
- Correspondence (Box 46D)
  A.Comments by Samuel Untermeyer on the Currency Bill; Speech by Carter Glass, September 1920, on currency reform and the Federal Reserve act; Letter from President Woodrow Wilson regarding personnel of the Committee on banking and currency; William G. McAdoo to Carter Glass, Paul M. Warburg to William G. McAdoo, 2 August 1916; Letter of Coolidge to Carter Glass, 30 July 1935; Letter of T. J. Coolidge to Carter Glass regarding direct loans to the treasury; Letter of Joseph Kennedy regarding "job" as Federal Reserve agent, February 1936.
- Correspondence (Box 46E)
  A. Letter to Carter Glass from John Randolph Bolling relative to "story" by Carter Glass, 31 July 1926; Ray Stannard Baker to Carter Glass, 28 July 1926, regarding manuscript sent to Baker by Carter Glass and Baker's comments; Edwin R. Seligman to Carter Glass regarding Paul M. Warburg; Charles S. Hamlin to Carter Glass, 31 August 1926, regarding Glass articles; Letter from Oliver J. Sands to Carter Glass regarding eligible paper, 18 May 1932; Letter from Oliver J. Sands to Carter Glass, 12 February 1932, regarding accounts payable by banks; Letter to Carter Glass from Phillips urging appointment of Oliver J. Sands to the Federal Reserve; Oliver J. Sands to Carter Glass regarding foreign bonds in the assets of banks, 15 December 1931; Oliver J. Sands to Carter Glass, 13 February 1932, regarding reserve bank loans to commercial banks; Atlee Bomersee to Carter Glass, 29 February 1932, regarding Federal Reserve credit and available eligible paper; Letter of Carter Glass to Burleson regarding appointment to Paul M. Warburg to Board of Governors, 16 April 1914; Letter of Daiger to Rixey Smith regarding Samuel Untermeyer; Editorial in Lynchburg Advance, regarding interference with foreign credits by Federal Reserve System; Memo regarding Cuban bonds and a Committee relative thereto; Letter, 20 August 1934, H. Parker Willis to Carter Glass regarding Paul M. Warburg and Federal Reserve act, and work to be done by Bogen and Beckhart for Carter Glass; Robert Sterling Clark to Grayson; Review of Carter Glass' book by Warren G. Harding; A. D. Smith's four articles in New York Times on the founders of the Federal Reserve System; W. P. G. Harding review of Carter Glass' History of the Federal Reserve in New York Evening Post, 19 March 1929.
- Miscellaneous Papers and Correspondenc 1898-1918 (1909-1913) (Box 47)
  A. Lists of thousands of names of people from various counties in Virginia, presumably names of eligible voters or registered democrats in a certain district of the state.
  B. Item dealing with banking legislation, including drafts of proposed laws and a list of questions for witnesses appearing before the Committee on Banking and Currency as well as other such material.